またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
ちゃんと猫らしくしてろよ 先生
Try to act like a real cat, sensei.
全く 何だってこんなに遠出せねばならんのだ
Geez, why do we have to go so far?
What are you talking about?
何言ってんだよ
先生が最近太り過ぎだから 散歩に付き合ってやってるんじゃないか
You've gotten fat recently, so I'm taking you on a walk.
あら 地震かしら
Oh? Is it an earthquake?
It's gotten cooler, so my fur just sticks out more.
涼しくなって 毛が伸びただけだ 阿呆が
お バッタだ
It's a grasshopper! A grasshopper!
バッタ バッタが動いてる
The grasshopper's moving! The grasshopper!
バッタ
Ah, geez...
もう
ごめん 居眠りしてしまって
Sorry, I was kind of dozing off.
大丈夫
Are you all right?
あ はい
Y-Yes.
そう よかった
I see, that's good.
刺青
A tattoo?
Th-Thanks.
ど どうも
名取さん 休憩終わりでーす
Natori-san! The break's over!
あ はーい 行きまーす
Okay, I'm coming!
今の名取周一じゃない
Wasn't that Natori Shuuichi?
Natori Shuuichi? Who's that?
名取周一 誰それ
やだ 今売り出し中の俳優よ
Come on, he's the actor who recently became popular.
Don't you know him?
知らないの
That was surprising.
びっくりした
一瞬先生が化けたのかと思った
I thought sensei disguised himself for a moment.
名取さんのロング先やって その後
First you'll have an argument, and then...
名取 周一
Natori... Shuuichi...
Ayakashi Exorcism
A rope?
縄
Is it tied to her?
繋がれてるのか 妖怪 だよな
She's a Youkai, right?
おい 包帯が解けかけてるぞ
Hey, your bandages are coming apart.
巻き直そうか
Want me to tie them back up for you?
人のくせに構うな
You're just a human, so don't talk to me.
Idiot, don't just talk to them without giving it any thought, Natsume.
馬鹿者 やたらと声をかけるな 夏目
Yeah.
That's right.
そうだった 声なんかかけて
Why am I calling out to them?
嘘つき 嘘つき
Liar!
Natsume-kun, why do you keep making up all these creepy lies?
夏目君 どうしてまたそんな気味悪い嘘ばかりつくの
いい加減 ちょっと前のことくらい 忘れたっていいだろうに
Why can't I at least forget about what happened recently?
あれ 先生は
Huh? Where's sensei?
Gone
drinking
またか
Again?
何だあれ
What is that?
Let go!
放せ
あ これは
This is...
キミ 大丈夫か
Are you all right?
見られたか
He saw me?
No, it's not like he could see that thing just now.
いや どうせこの人に 今の奴は見えてない
大丈夫です
I'm all right. It was nothing, so you don't need to worry.
何でもないので 構わず
キミ 今のが見えるのかい
You...
You could see the thing just now?
俺も見える
I can see them too.
見えるって 何が
See them?
See what?
Let's see...
そうだな
おそらく 妖怪と呼ばれるものの類い
Probably the ones called Youkai.
そんな
No way...
Just who are you?
あなたは一体
Huh? You can't tell?
あれ 分からないかな
昼間一度会ってるだろう
We met once this afternoon.
おれは名取 名取周一
I'm Natori. Natori Shuuichi.
試させてもらったら 見えるようだし
I tested you, and it seems you can see them.
何か力も強いようだ
And your power seems to be quite strong.
で 惚けてしまったか ごめんな
Sorry, I'm getting too excited.
I was just so happy.
嬉しかったんでつい
俺とキミは仲間だよ
You and I are the same.
な 仲間
Th-The same?
いってきます
I'm going now.
Ah, wait, Takashi-kun!
あ 待って 貴志君
You forgot your lunch.
忘れてるわよ お弁当
Ah, shoot!
あ いけない
What's wrong? You seem out of it this morning.
どうしたの 今朝はなんだかぼんやりして
No, it's nothing.
いえ 別に
いってきます
I'm going to go now.
And finally, the sisters brought the corpse that no one else would take to the gate.
とうとうしまいには
引き取り手のない死人を この門へ持ってきて
俺とキミは 仲間だよ
You and I are the same.
The same?
仲間 試したとか言ってたけど
He said he tested me. Was he teasing me or something?
もしかして からかわれてるのか
おい 夏目
Hey, Natsume.
大丈夫か
You okay?
え 田沼
Tanuma... Yeah, I'm okay.
うん 大丈夫
しっかりしろ
Get it together!
くそ こんなに動揺してしまうなんて
Damn it, how can I be so confused like this?
ねえ あの門のところ 俳優の名取周一に似てない
Hey, doesn't that person by the gate look like the actor Natori Shuuichi?
え あ 本当だ 似てるかも
Ah, you're right, he kind of does.
へえ 名取周一だ
It's Natori Shuuichi.
知ってるのか
You know him?
Hey, don't make fun of me.
バカにするなよ
俺だってテレビくらい見るさ
Even I watch some TV.
But, well, if I had to say, he's the type that I wouldn't like.
まあ どちらかというと 苦手なタイプだけどな ああいうの
Walk further away from me.
もっと離れて歩いてくださいよ
なんで
Why?
目立つの嫌なんです
I don't like standing out.
I'm sorry for being so fabulous.
きらめいててごめん
話がしたいんだ
I just want to have a talk.
So, could you come with me for a bit?
少し付き合ってくれないか
So, you're really human.
キミ 本当に人だったんだね
気配が不思議だから 実は妖怪なんじゃないかと思ったよ
Your aura was kind of weird, so I thought you might have been a Youkai.
用件は何ですか
What do you want?
キミ 私の仕事 手伝ってみないかい
Would you like to help me with my job?
仕事って まさかテレビの
Your job? Do you mean your TV one?
No, my side job.
いや 裏の仕事さ
I actually work as an exorcist too.
実は私は お祓い家業もやっていてね
お祓い
An exorcist?
ちょうど助手が欲しかったんだ
I've been wanting an assistant.
キミにとってもいい勉強になると思うんだが
I'm sure you'll learn a lot from it, so how about it?
どうだい 一度
嫌ですよ
No thanks.
How selfish.
わがままだな
Is it the money? Do you want money?
あ 金かい
金が欲しいのかい
I'm leaving.
帰ります
冗談冗談
I'm just joking!
気が短いな
You're so quick-tempered.
あ あれ あの刺青 あんな形だったっけ
Huh? Did that tattoo look like that?
刺青が動いた
The tattoo moved!
Ah, amazing!
あ すごいな
キミにはこれも見えるのか
You can see this too?
身体中を動き回るんだよ この痣
This birthmark moves all around my body.
Birthmark?
痣
When I was young, I noticed that I had a birthmark around my ankle.
幼い頃 くるぶし辺りに痣ができたのに気付いてね
次の日に消えたと思ったら 左腕に移動していたんだ
The next day, I thought it had disappeared,
but it had moved to my left arm.
気味悪くてね
It was pretty creepy.
After looking it up, I found out that it was a Youkai.
調べてみたら どうやら妖怪だと分かったんだ
対処法を知ろうと いろいろ勉強したよ
I learned a lot while trying to find a way to get rid of it.
独学だけどね
It was all self-study, though.
体調に影響は
Does it have any effect on you?
特にないから かえって不気味でね
Not really, so I just left it.
実は寿命を食われてましたとかだったら困るんだよな
It actually eats your life-span or something...
This person has been fighting alone under all that uneasiness.
この人は ずっとそんな不安と一人で戦って
笑い事ですか
That's nothing to laugh about!
Master.
主様
なんです その生意気なガキは
Who is this precocious little brat?
あ あの お客様 どうかなさいました
Ah, is something wrong?
I think he has anemia.
貧血かな
Sorry, but could you bring some water?
すまないが 水を
Yes!
はい
Hey, hey, don't act on your own.
こらこら 勝手なまねをするな
He's my precious friend.
私の大切な友人だ
失礼は許さないぞ
I won't allow you to be rude to him.
失礼はお前だ
You're the rude one.
Don't speak so friendly to my prey, brat.
私の獲物に気安く声をかけるな ガキが
ニャン
Sensei!
先生
キミ その珍妙な生き物は
What's that odd creature?
Sir, we can't have you bringing in a cat!
お客様 猫ちゃんの連れ込みは困ります
S-Sorry!
す すいません
He's so funny, no matter how many times I look!
何度見ても面白いね
What is he?
これ何だい
A-Ah, he's my cat.
え ええと 家の猫です
Cat?
猫 へえ
いえ 嘘です
No, I lied.
Nyanko-sensei isn't actually a cat.
にゃんこ先生は
本当は猫じゃなくて
Thanks. I see.
ありがとう
そうか 可愛い子分さんだねえ
You've got a cute follower.
I'm not his follower! I'm his master, you greenhorn!
子分じゃなくて 師匠だ 青二才
Bastard! What are you doing to my master, you fat cat?
おのれ 主様に何をする ブタ猫が
What'd you say, frizzy?!
何だとこのちりちりパーマ
Hey, hold it.
あ こら
先生
Stop!
FAT
CAT
FRIZZY
やめろ
Stop!
Allow me to introduce you.
紹介しよう
On my right is Sasago, and on my left is Urihime.
右が笹後 左が瓜姫
使役している妖怪だ
They're Youkai that serve me.
I have a job from a certain old family.
今回 ある旧家からの依頼があってね
They have a "forbidden" cellar that supposedly curses you if you open it.
開けると呪われると言われている開かずの倉があったんだけど
財政難で質屋を呼んだ
They needed money, so they called for a pawner.
The pawner opened the cellar with the key he kept and went in with the family head to have a look.
鍵を預かった質屋が倉を開け
主人共々物色した
それ以来 倉を開けた質屋は毎夜うなされ
Ever since then, the pawner would have nightmares every night,
be in accidents, and have bad luck.
事故に遭いかけるなど 不吉なことが起こっているらしい
Is it the doing of a Youkai?
それって 妖怪の仕業ですか
That's what these two say after looking into it.
調べてきたこの二匹はそう言っている
Ever since their ancestors locked away their valuables in order to save up,
ご先祖が金目のものを貯め込んで封印して以来
a Youkai began to live in the cellar and deny entrance to humans.
妖怪がその倉に住み着き 人の侵入を拒んでいる
全く困ったものだ
What a troublemaker.
奴らはいつも理不尽で迷惑な存在だな
They're always so irrational and such an annoyance.
I'm not so sure.
そうですかね
You can't say anything unless you know their circumstances.
事情が分からないと何とも
You're a nice kid.
キミは優しいね
You're on the Youkai's side?
妖怪の肩を持つのかい
そう言う言い方は
That attitude is...
So you wear glasses, Natori-san.
あ 名取さんはメガネをするんですね
These are fake.
これ だてだよ
It's easier to see Youkai through glasses or mirrors instead of the naked eye.
妖怪を見るときは肉眼で見るより見えやすいんだ
ガラスや鏡を通した方がね
へえ
ブレスレットみたいだ
It's like a bracelet.
That's the first time I've seen you smile.
初めて笑ったね
I guess this birthmark is useful at times.
この痣も役に立つことがあるんだな
キミは優しい子だよ
You're a nice kid.
You're just a nice kid.
優しい ただの子供だよ
So...
だから 何も恥じることはないんだよ
There's nothing to be ashamed of.
Sorry.
すみません
I'll be at the pawner's employer's house tomorrow.
じゃあ 明日 質屋の主人の自宅
I'll be waiting for you there.
ここで待ってるよ
I didn't say I'd help you yet.
まだ 手伝うなんて言ってませんよ
Natsume.
夏目
Hand over the Book of Friends!
寄越せ 友人帳を
There's something in that thicket.
あの茂み 何かいる
I have to get away or Natori-san will get involved.
離れないと 名取さんを巻き込む
夏目
I'll be going now.
あの じゃあ 俺はこれで
I told you, you don't need to keep any secrets.
言ったろ キミがこそこそすることはない
Hand it over!
寄越せ
Stop it already! He's wounded!
止めてください もう手負いですよ
What are you saying?
何を言ってるんだ キミを狙ってるんだぞ
He's after you.
It's okay now.
もう大丈夫ですって
You're naive.
甘いよ
人を襲うのを許しておける分けないだろう
You cannot let them hurt people.
Is this what you do to exorcise Youkai?
貴方の妖怪払いって こんなことなんですか
Hurting them is going too far!
傷を負わせるのはやり過ぎですよ
妖怪に苦しめられてるキミなら 分かるだろう
You should understand, since Youkai have made you suffer.
But I can't approve of this method!
でも こういうやり方ならば
賛同できません
そういう鬱陶しい考え方してると
If you have that kind of annoying mindset, it'll come right back to bite you.
しわ寄せが自分に返ってくるよ
Even so, this is a method I can approve.
それでも
その方が俺には納得できます
Thank you for saving me.
助けてくれて ありがとうございました
Even though I finally met someone who can see the same things,
せっかく 同じものが見える人と出会えたのに
その人とさえ分かり合うのは難しいことなのか
is it too hard to understand each other?
We both suffered through the same things too.
同じ痛みを 超えてきたはずなのに
I could see the hate he had for Ayakashi when I touched him for a moment.
奴に触れられた一瞬 妖ものへの憎しみが見えたよ
Despite what he says, he must've gone through a lot with them.
なんだかんだ言って 妖ではいろいろ苦労したんだろう
誰からも 信じてもらえずに
Without anyone believing in him.
This rope...
この縄
Stop it, boy.
止めんか 小童
Ah, sorry.
あ ああ ごめん
Who put this rope on you?
この縄は だれが
You have his smell.
お前 あの子の匂いがする
His?
あの子
それ 気になるから 巻き直させてくれないか
It's been on my mind, so could you let me fix your bandages?
You can ignore me when I finish.
済んだらもう無視してくれていいからさ
A...
どこぞの
A long time ago, a shaman tied this rope to me.
昔 どこぞの祈祷師がこの縄を
I used to be a mountain guardian,
私は山守をしていたが 捕まってあの柱に縛られ
but I was caught, tied to that pole, and ordered to protect this family and cellar.
この家と倉を守るように命じられた
So you were always here.
じゃあ いつも
最近 倉を開けたものがいる
There was someone who opened the cellar recently.
役目を果たさねば やがてこの縄が絞まり 首が落ちる
If I don't fulfill my duty, this rope will constrict and my head will fall off.
Her nails...
あ 爪が
I tried to run away once,
昔は逃げようとしたが
やがて諦めた
but I eventually gave up.
諦めて 一人ぼーっとここに座っていた
I gave up and just sat here alone in a daze...
For years and years...
何年も 何年も
Hey, what's wrong?
ねえ どうしたの
What a strange mask.
変なお面
Your hands are bleeding.
手から血が出てるよ
It was a human child.
あれは人の子だった
Like you, he could see me.
お前のように 私を見ることができた
He tied this for me.
その子がこれを巻いてくれた
When the cellar opened, I thought it would've been okay to not fulfill my duty and to have my head fall off.
倉が開いた時 役目など果たさず
このまま首が落ちるのもいいと思った
I had no regrets.
何の未練もない
But fate is a funny thing.
けれど 縁にしては面白いものだ
あの子が祓い人としてこの町へ帰ってきた
That child has come back to this city as an exorcist.
I would be happy to be a service to that child.
あの子の手柄になるのは喜ばしい
Yin and Yang are so troublesome.
異形とは面倒だね
こんな布切れ一枚の礼もろくにできない
I can't even thank him for this single strip of cloth.
Hey, I thought you wouldn't come.
やあ もう来ないかと思った
Rip up the paper there and cover up the characters on the ground.
その和紙を千切って 地面に書いてある陣を消してくれ
名取さんは 今日祓う妖怪のことを 知ってるんですか
Do you know the Youkai you're exorcising today, Natori-san?
Yeah, it's an enslaved Youkai with a rope around its neck.
ああ 首に縄をかけられた自由のない妖怪らしい
It should be exorcised.
祓ってやるべきだろう
Natori-san doesn't remember her.
やっぱり 名取さんは覚えてないんだ
I have to stop her from coming here!
ここに来るのを 止めさせないと
Where are you going?
どこへ行く気だい
I can't have you interfering.
邪魔されると困るね
Just stay still.
そこで大人しくしていな
Natori-san!
名取さん
It's coming.
来る
Stop, Natori-san!
名取さん だめだ
Stop, child.
止めろ 人の子
You can't do anything, so stop.
何もできんよ およし
Stop!
止めろ
Hurry up and get out!
早く出なさい
I can't stop the spell!
私には雷を止められない
先生
Sensei...
Hey, what's wrong?
ねえ どうしたの
What a strange mask.
変なお面
Your hand is bleeding.
手から血が出てるよ
When I fell, my mom treated me this way.
転んだ時 母さんがこうして手当てしてくれたんだ
My mom isn't around anymore, though.
でも 母さんはもういない
She had a weak body.
からだが弱かったんだ
The old men say I called forth bad luck because I can see weird things.
僕が変なもの見るせいで
不幸を招き寄せたんだって 伯父さん達はそう言ってた
But if so, someone should've just gotten rid of me before that happened.
でもさ だったらそうなる前に
誰かが僕を退治してくれればよかったのに
You talk a lot, child.
よく喋るガキだ
I'm not a child, I'm Shuuichi.
ガキじゃないよ 周一だよ
You know, human children do not have the power to call forth bad luck.
人はね
人の子には 不幸を招く力なんてないんだよ
Really?
本当
You're a nice child.
お前は優しい子だよ
You're just a nice child.
優しいただの子供だよ
Because I was so happy...
だって 私はお前に会えて
こんなに 嬉しかったのだから
Just to meet you...
I didn't realize it.
気が付かなかったよ
It was that Youkai.
あの妖怪だったんだな 首の呪縛も焼き切れた
The curse on her neck has been lifted.
I thought the chances would be 50/50.
五分五分だと思っていたんだ
If it was a helpless Youkai that couldn't be freed from its curse,
呪縛から逃れられない 哀れな妖怪なら
I wanted to let them go in peace.
一思いに逝かせてやりたがったし
And if it had gone well, then perhaps the rope would've burned off and it'd be free.
うまく行けば一命を取り留めて
縄を焼いて自由にしてやれるんじゃないかって
I'm glad you saved her.
助かってよかったよ
けど夏目 すまなかった
I'm sorry though, Natsume.
こういう巻き込み方をしたかった訳じゃない
I didn't want to get you involved like this.
When I look at you, it reminds me of my old self,
キミを見ていると 昔の自分を思い出して
and I thought I could teach you something.
何かを伝えてやれるんじゃないかと
I just wanted to talk.
ただ話をしていたかったんだ
はい 僕もです
Yeah, me too.
Well, I can't have someone reckless like you as my assistant.
まったく キミのような無茶なのは助手にできないな
Really? That's unfortunate.
そうですか それは残念だ
You're not cute at all.
可愛くないな
What about you? Why did you become so peevish?
そっちこそ なんだってそんなにやさぐれちゃったんです
You were such a pure child.
小さい頃は純粋だったのに
What'd you say?
うん 何だって
甘いと言われようと あなたのやり方には賛同できません
Even if you call me naive, I can't approve of your methods.
That's fine too.
それもいいさ
We don't need to have the same opinion on everything.
何も同じ意見でなければならないということもないだろう
Understanding others is a difficult thing.
他人と分かり合うのは難しいことだよ
For everyone, you see.
誰にとってもね
If you're ever in trouble, you can call me anytime.
困ったことがあったら いつでも言ってくれ
私も友人の力になりたいからな
I want to be helpful to my friend too.
That Youkai girl is finally free,
あの妖怪の女の子 せっかく自由になれたっていうのに
yet she was given the name Hiiragi and is going to serve Natori.
柊という名前をもらって
今度は名取さんに仕えるなんて
It seems to be her own will, though.
自分の意志だったみたいだけどさ
Maybe she's fallen for him.
惚れた相手なんじゃないか
Well, there are times when only they themselves know what makes them happy.
まあ 個人の喜びなど 本人にしか分からないこともあるさ
Yeah.
そうだな
That's right.
そうだよな
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
夕立の雨上がりに
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
Asagi's Koto
人の子よ その体をしばらく貸してくれ
Human child, please lend me your body for a while.
No way!
冗談じゃないぞ
That's right, he's mine!
そうだ こいつは私のものだ
Since when was I yours, sensei?
いつ先生のものになった
アサギに もう一度だけ琴を弾かせてやりたいんだ
Please let me play the koto one more time.
Please, I don't have much time left.
頼む もう時間がない